<!-- -*-  mode: nxml -*- -->
<!--
    fortran95.xml: "Fortran Language" chapter

Copyright (C) 1994  Geoffrey Furnish and Maurice LeBrun
Copyright (C) 1999, 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003  Rafael Laboissiere
Copyright (C) 1999-2016 Alan W. Irwin
Copyright (C) 2003  Joao Cardoso

Redistribution and use in source (XML DocBook) and "compiled" forms
(HTML, PDF, PostScript, DVI, TeXinfo and so forth) with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
met:

1. Redistributions of source code (XML DocBook) must retain the
above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following
disclaimer as the first lines of this file unmodified.

2. Redistributions in compiled form (transformed to other DTDs,
converted to HTML, PDF, PostScript, and other formats) must
reproduce the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and
the following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other
materials provided with the distribution.

Important: THIS DOCUMENTATION IS PROVIDED BY THE PLPLOT PROJECT "AS IS"
AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,
THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE PLPLOT PROJECT BE LIABLE
FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR
CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF
SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR
BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY,
WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR
OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS DOCUMENTATION,
EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
-->

<chapter id="fortran95"> <title>Fortran Language</title>

<para>The new implemention of the Fortran binding of PLplot takes full
advantage of the <literal>ISO_C_BINDING</literal> feature of the
Fortran 2003 standard, which is supported by all current compilers.
The advantage of this approach is that the entire binding is now
written in Fortran, so that there is only one library that calling
programs need to link against.  Furthermore, the binding defines
overloaded routines for the case of either single- or double-precision
arguments supplied by the calling programme regardless of the floating-point
precision of the underlying C library.  That makes this binding much
easier to use than our previous implementation of the Fortran binding
where calling routines were forced to use the same floating-point precision that was
configured for the underlying PLplot C library.</para>

<para> Note: in this chapter <quote>Fortran</quote> stands for
<quote>Fortran as defined by the Fortran 2003 standard</quote>.  Older
versions of PLplot supported FORTRAN 77, but the binding for this 40
years old version has been abandoned for quite a few years now.  As we
now use features from the Fortran 2003 standard, it is no longer
appropriate to refer to the language as Fortran 95.  </para>

<para>We illustrate the implementation of our Fortran binding using the
<literal>&plstring;</literal> API as an example.  The
summary of the C
API for that routine which best serves our purposes here is
<programlisting>
void plstring( PLINT n, const PLFLT *x, const PLFLT *y, const char *string );
</programlisting>
The arguments <literal>n</literal>, <literal>x</literal>,
<literal>y</literal>, and <literal>string</literal> represent the
number of times the string is plotted, the arrays of length
<literal>n</literal> which contain the <literal>x, y</literal> values where that string is plotted, and
the NULL-terminated C string that contains the ordinary (not
wide) characters in the UTF-8 encoding of a unicode glyph to be
plotted.  The PLplot <literal>PLINT</literal> type is normally defined
as the C fundamental type <literal>int32_t</literal>, and the PLplot
<literal>PLFLT</literal> type is defined to be one of the two C
fundamental types <literal>float</literal> or
<literal>double</literal> depending on how the C PLplot library
is configured.</para>

<para>Here is an example of one fairly typical Fortran call of <literal>plstring</literal>.
<programlisting>
program test_plplot
    use plplot
    implicit none
    integer, parameter :: my_real  = kind(1.0)
    real(kind=my_real), dimension(6) :: x, y
    ...
    x = ...
    y = ...
    ...
    call plstring(x,y,"+")
    ...
end program test_plplot
</programlisting>
where for this particular case <literal>x</literal> and <literal>y</literal> are arrays with 6
elements defined and the points are to be plotted using the ascii "+"
symbol (although if you are using a unicode-aware PLplot device, then
you can try many other unicode possibilities for the symbol such as
the U+22C5 DOT OPERATOR, "⋅").  Note that our Fortran binding
implementation below allows use of the <literal>kind(1.0d0)</literal> choice of
<literal>my_real</literal> precision as well.</para>

<para>The <literal>plstring</literal>-relevant parts of the <literal>plplot</literal> module used above are
<programlisting>
module plplot
    ...
    use plplot_single
    use plplot_double
    ...
end module plplot
</programlisting>
The redacted part of the <literal>plplot</literal> module implements the interfaces to
the PLplot C library routines that happen to have no floating-point
arguments very similarly to the way that the <literal>plplot_single</literal> and
<literal>plplot_double</literal> modules interface the PLplot C routines like &plstring;
that do include floating-point arguments.  The <literal>plstring</literal>-relevant parts of the
<literal>plplot_single</literal> module are
<programlisting>
module plplot_single
    ...
    integer, parameter :: wp = private_single
    ...
    interface plstring
        module procedure plstring_impl
    end interface plstring
    private :: plstring_impl
    ...
contains
    ...
    subroutine plstring_impl( x, y, string )

       real(kind=wp), dimension (:), intent(in) :: x, y
       character(len=*), intent(in) :: string

       integer(kind=private_plint) :: n_local

       interface
           subroutine interface_plstring( n, x, y, string ) bind(c,name='c_plstring')
               import :: private_plint, private_plflt
               implicit none
               integer(kind=private_plint), value, intent(in) :: n
               real(kind=private_plflt), dimension(*), intent(in) :: x, y
               character(len=1), dimension(*), intent(in) :: string
           end subroutine interface_plstring
       end interface

       n_local = size(x, kind=private_plint)
       if(n_local /= size(y, kind=private_plint) ) then
           write(error_unit,"(a)") "Plplot Fortran Warning: plstring: inconsistent sizes for x and y"
       end if

       call interface_plstring( n_local, real(x,kind=private_plflt), real(y,kind=private_plflt), &amp;
           trim(string)//c_null_char )
    end subroutine plstring_impl
    ...
end module plplot_single
</programlisting>
The <literal>plstring</literal>-relevant parts of the <literal>plplot_double</literal> module are defined
identically (in fact that identicality is guaranteed by using the
same included file to define the identical parts) except for
<programlisting>
    integer, parameter :: wp = private_double
</programlisting>
</para>

<para>Here are some notes on the above implementation of our Fortran
binding for <literal>plstring</literal>.  The
<literal>plplot_single</literal> and <literal>plplot_double</literal>
modules implement two versions of the Fortran
<literal>plstring</literal> subroutine which are identical except one
subroutine has floating-point arguments with a kind value of
<literal>wp = private_single = kind(1.0)</literal> and one subroutine
has floating-point arguments with kind value of <literal>wp =
private_double = kind(1.0d0)</literal>.  The result is the Fortran
compiler automatically chooses the correct overloaded version of
<literal>plstring</literal> that corresponds to the precision of the
floating-point arguments used by the program (e.g., like
<literal>test_plplot</literal> above) that is being compiled.  The
intrinsic function <literal>size()</literal> is used to determine the
size of arrays and allows checking that their dimensions are
consistent with each other when the C implementation uses a common
size for the arrays as in the <literal>plstring</literal> case. (See also,
<filename>bindings/f95/README_array_sizes</filename>.)  The
intrinsic function <literal>real()</literal> is used to convert
floating-point data between the type used by the calling routine and
the type used by the underlying PLplot C library, and the intrinsic
function <literal>int()</literal> (not used in the above example) is
used for similarly converting integer data.  The intrinsic function
<literal>trim()</literal> and the <literal>ISO_C_BINDING</literal>
parameter <literal>c_null_char</literal> are used to help convert
a Fortran character string into a NULL-terminated C string.
Also note the above interface block defining
<literal>subroutine interface_plstring</literal> is the
Fortran representation of the exact C API of &plstring;. </para>

<para> Here is a table summarizing how C data types correspond to
Fortran data types in the arguments of functions defined by our
Fortran binding.  Consult the Fortran code in
<filename>bindings/f95/*</filename> for further details of how the
conversion is done between our private Fortran types that are
equivalent to the corresponding C types, and the public Fortran types
that are available for Fortran function arguments in our Fortran
binding.  Note the <literal>my_flt</literal> kind value used in this
table is not provided by our Fortran binding.  Instead it merely
indicates that the calling routine (e.g., the
<literal>test_plplot</literal> example routine above) has the choice
of either <literal>kind(1.0)</literal> or
<literal>kind(1.0d0)</literal> for the kind values of the
floating-point arguments of the PLplot functions defined by our
Fortran binding.
    <informaltable frame="all" colsep="1" rowsep="1" pgwide="0">
      <tgroup align="left" cols="3">
        <colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colnum="3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>C type</entry><entry>Private Fortran type</entry><entry>Public Fortran type</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><literal>PLFLT</literal></entry><entry><literal>real(kind=private_plflt)</literal></entry><entry><literal>real(kind=my_flt)</literal></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><literal>PLFLT *</literal></entry><entry><literal>real(kind=private_plflt), dimension(*)</literal></entry><entry><literal>real(kind=my_flt), dimension(:)</literal></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><literal>PLFLT **</literal></entry><entry><literal>type(c_ptr), dimension(*)</literal></entry><entry><literal>real(kind=my_flt), dimension(:, :)</literal></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><literal>PLINT</literal></entry><entry><literal>integer(kind=private_plint)</literal></entry><entry><literal>integer</literal></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><literal>PLINT *</literal></entry><entry><literal>integer(kind=private_plint), dimension(*)</literal></entry><entry><literal>integer, dimension(:)</literal></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><literal>PLBOOL</literal></entry><entry><literal>integer(kind=private_plbool)</literal></entry><entry><literal>logical</literal></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry><literal>char *</literal></entry><entry><literal>character(len=1), dimension(*)</literal></entry><entry><literal>character(len=*)</literal></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
In C there are two ways to pass a variable --- by value (the default)
or by reference (pointer), whereas in Fortran this difference is not
visible in the call, only in the interface definition via the
<literal>value</literal> attribute.  Therefore when you see references
in the documentation of our C API to <emphasis>either</emphasis> an
ordinary argument or a pointer argument (e.g.
<literal>*data</literal>), you simply use an ordinary Fortran variable
or array name.  The new Fortran binding automatically takes care of
any conversion that may be necessary.  </para>

<para>In sum, the <literal>plstring</literal> example above
illustrates the way our Fortran binding makes the PLplot C API
conveniently accessible from Fortran while letting the C binding and
overloading features of the Fortran compiler hide the complexities of
the name mangling that occurs.</para>

<para>Users should be aware that there are a few cases with our new Fortran binding where we provide
double-precision floating-point entities but no equivalent single-precision floating-point alternative.
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>
        The Fortran standard dictates that compilers cannot disambiguate
        overloaded functions based on the type of their return value.  This
        means that the &plrandd; function cannot be
        disambiguated because it has no arguments.  For this reason we have
        decided to provide only one version of this function that
        returns a double-precision random value.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        The Fortran standard dictates that compilers cannot disambiguate
        overloaded routines based on the types of arguments to callback
        routines that appear as arguments to those routines.  This means that
        the &plstransform; and &plslabelfunc; routines cannot be disambiguated
        because they have no <emphasis>direct</emphasis> floating-point
        arguments.  For this reason we have decided that for the case where
        <literal>plstransform</literal> uses a
        <literal>transform_coordinate</literal> callback as its first
        argument, that callback will be allowed to only have double-precision
        arguments.  And similarly for <literal>plslabelfunc</literal> and the
        <literal>label_func</literal> callback.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        The new Fortran binding defines a derived <literal>PLGraphicsIn</literal> type as follows:
        <programlisting>
  type :: PLGraphicsIn
     integer                   :: type           ! of event (CURRENTLY UNUSED)
     integer                   :: state          ! key or button mask
     integer                   :: keysym         ! key selected
     integer                   :: button         ! mouse button selected
     integer                   :: subwindow      ! subwindow (alias subpage, alias subplot) number
     character(len=16)         :: string         ! Fortran character string
     integer                   :: pX, pY         ! absolute device coordinates of pointer
     real(kind=private_double) :: dX, dY         ! relative device coordinates of pointer
     real(kind=private_double) :: wX, wY         ! world coordinates of pointer
  end type PLGraphicsIn
        </programlisting>
        This is the type that should be used for the argument of the Fortran
        <literal>plGetCursor</literal> routine.  We provide no alternative
        <literal>plGetCursor</literal> routine whose argument is similar to
        <literal>PLGraphicsIn</literal> but with single-precision
        <literal>dX</literal>, <literal>dY</literal>, <literal>wX</literal>,
        and <literal>wY</literal> components.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        The new Fortran binding provides three auxiliary floating-point parameters,
        <literal>PL_PI</literal>, <literal>PL_TWOPI</literal> and <literal>PL_NOTSET</literal> which are
        all defined in double precision. If the calling routine requires single precision instead it
        should define a local parameter as in the following code fragment:
        <programlisting>
    use plplot
    ...
    integer, parameter :: my_flt = kind(1.0)
    real(kind=my_flt), parameter :: my_NOTSET = PL_NOTSET
        </programlisting>
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>Users should be aware that the new Fortran binding for PLplot enforces the following interfacing rules:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>The new Fortran binding interfaces Fortran functions/subroutines with
      C routines if the C routines provide/do not provide a return value.  For example, this rule means
      that the C &plparseopts; routine that returns an error code must be invoked at the
      Fortran level similarly to the following:
      <programlisting>
    integer :: plplarseopts_rc
    ...
    plparseopts_rc = plparseopts(...)
      </programlisting>
      Of course, this rule means it is possible for Fortran routines invoking functions like plparseopts to respond properly
      to error conditions returned by the corresponding C routine.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para> Only the redacted form of Fortran API (with all redundant dimension
      arguments removed) is supported.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>If the C API for the function being interfaced
      includes a size value corresponding to identical sizes of dimension(s)
      of multiple array arguments. then the sizes of the corresponding
      dimensions of the Fortran arrays must also be identical.  The complete
      list of these adopted rules for consistently sized array arguments for
      our Fortran binding are given at <filename>bindings/f95/README_array_sizes</filename>.
      These rules are enforced in a user-friendly way by issuing a run-time
      warning whenever these rules have been violated.  For those cases which
      generate such warnings because the calling
      routine has specified static or allocatable arrays whose
      relevant defined areas are smaller than their size, use the normal
      Fortran rules for array slicing to specify completely defined arrays
      with consistent sizes that comply with this interfacing rule.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Fortran logical arguments are used for all cases where
      the corresponding C argument is <literal>PLBOOL</literal>.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>All floating-point arguments for a given function call
      must have consistent kind values (either <literal>kind(1.0)</literal>
      or <literal>kind(1.0.d0)</literal>).</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>For more information on calling PLplot from Fortran, please consult
the example Fortran programs in <filename>examples/f95</filename> that are
distributed with PLplot.  For more information on building your own
PLplot-related Fortran routines, please consult either the traditional
(Makefile + pkg-config) or CMake-based build systems that are created
as part of the install step for our Fortran (and other language)
examples.</para>
</chapter>
