<!-- -*-  mode: nxml -*- -->
<!--
    intro.xml: "Introduction" chapter

Copyright (C) 1994  Geoffrey Furnish and Maurice LeBrun
Copyright (C) 1999, 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003  Alan W. Irwin
Copyright (C) 1999, 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004  Rafael Laboissiere
Copyright (C) 2003  Joao Cardoso

Redistribution and use in source (XML DocBook) and "compiled" forms
(HTML, PDF, PostScript, DVI, TeXinfo and so forth) with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
met:

1. Redistributions of source code (XML DocBook) must retain the
above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following
disclaimer as the first lines of this file unmodified.

2. Redistributions in compiled form (transformed to other DTDs,
converted to HTML, PDF, PostScript, and other formats) must
reproduce the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and
the following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other
materials provided with the distribution.

Important: THIS DOCUMENTATION IS PROVIDED BY THE PLPLOT PROJECT "AS IS"
AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,
THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE PLPLOT PROJECT BE LIABLE
FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR
CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF
SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR
BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY,
WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR
OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS DOCUMENTATION,
EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
-->

<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <sect1 id="plplot-plotting-library">
    <title>The PLplot Plotting Library</title>

    <para>PLplot is a &features-cross-platform; software package for
    creating scientific plots whose (<ulink
    url="http://www.utf-8.com/">UTF-8</ulink>) plot symbols and text are
    limited in practice only by what <ulink
    url="http://www.utf-8.com/">Unicode</ulink>-aware system fonts are
    installed on a user's computer. The PLplot software, which is
    primarily licensed under <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html">the LGPL</ulink>, has a
    clean architecture that is organized as a core C library, separate
    language &features-bindings; for that library,
    and separate device drivers that are dynamically
    loaded by the core library which control how the plots are presented
    in &features-noninteractive; and &features-interactive; plotting
    contexts.</para>

    <para>The PLplot core library can be used to create standard x-y
    plots, semi-log plots, log-log plots, contour plots, 3D surface plots,
    mesh plots, bar charts and pie charts. Multiple graphs (of the same or
    different sizes) may be placed on a single page, and multiple pages
    are allowed for those device formats that support them.</para>

    <para> PLplot has core library support for plot symbols and text
    specified by the user in the UTF-8 encoding of Unicode. This means for
    our many Unicode-aware devices that plot symbols and text are only
    limited by the collection of glyphs normally available via installed
    system fonts. Furthermore, a large subset of our Unicode-aware devices
    also support complex text layout (CTL) languages such as Arabic,
    Hebrew, and Indic and Indic-derived CTL scripts such as Devanagari,
    Thai, Lao, and Tibetan. Thus, for these PLplot devices essentially any
    language that is supported by Unicode and installed system fonts can
    be used to label plots.</para>

    <para>
      PLplot was originally developed by Sze Tan of the University of
      Auckland in Fortran-77.  Many of the underlying concepts used in the
      PLplot package are based on ideas used in Tim Pearson's PGPLOT
      package.  Sze Tan writes:
      <blockquote>
	<para>
	  I'm rather amazed how far PLPLOT has travelled given its origins
	  etc. I first used PGPLOT on the Starlink VAX computers while I was
	  a graduate student at the Mullard Radio Astronomy Observatory in
	  Cambridge from 1983-1987. At the beginning of 1986, I was to give a
	  seminar within the department at which I wanted to have a computer
	  graphics demonstration on an IBM PC which was connected to a
	  completely non-standard graphics card. Having about a week to do
	  this and not having any drivers for the card, I started from the
	  back end and designed PLPLOT to be such that one only needed to be
	  able to draw a line or a dot on the screen in order to do arbitrary
	  graphics.  The application programmer's interface was made as
	  similar as possible to PGPLOT so that I could easily port my
	  programs from the VAX to the PC.  The kernel of PLPLOT was modelled
	  on PGPLOT but the code is not derived from it.
	</para>
      </blockquote>
    </para>

    <para>The C version of PLplot was originally developed by Tony
    Richardson on a Commodore Amiga.  That version has been improved and
    expanded ever since first by Geoffrey Furnish and Maurice Lebrun in
    the 1990's and later (after the project was registered at SourceForge
    on 2000-02-23) <ulink
    url="http://plplot.sourceforge.net/credits.php">with a much-expanded
    development team.</ulink></para>

    <para>
      We welcome suggestions on how to improve this code, especially in
      the form of user-contributed enhancements or bug fixes.  If PLplot
      is used in any published papers, please include an acknowledgement
      or citation of our work, which will help us to continue improving
      PLplot.  Please direct all communication to the general PLplot
      mailing list, plplot-general@lists.sourceforge.net.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="features">
  <title>Feature Summary</title>
  <sect2 id="features-cross-platform">
    <title>Cross Platform</title>
    <para>PLplot is currently known to work on the following platforms:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Linux, Mac OS X, and other Unices</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>MSVC IDE on the Microsoft version of Windows (Windows 2000 and later)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Cygwin on the Microsoft version of Windows</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>MinGW-w64/MSYS2 on the Microsoft version of Windows</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>For each of the above platforms, PLplot can be built from <ulink url="http://plplot.sourceforge.net/downloads.php">source</ulink>, and for the Linux and Mac OS X platforms third-party binary packages for PLplot <ulink url="http://plplot.sourceforge.net/downloads.php#Binary_Packages">are available</ulink>.</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="features-bindings">
    <title>Language Bindings</title>
    <para>The language bindings of the C PLplot library are currently the following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Ada</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>C++</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>D</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Fortran 95</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Java</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://common-lisp.net/project/cl-plplot/">Lisp</ulink></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Lua</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>OCaml</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Octave</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://search.cpan.org/~dhunt/PDL-Graphics-PLplot">Perl/PDL</ulink></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Python</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Tcl/Tk</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="features-noninteractive">
    <title>Output File Formats</title>
    <para>PLplot device drivers support the following plotting file formats:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>CGM</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>GIF</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>JPEG</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PBM</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PDF</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PNG</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PostScript</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>SVG</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Xfig</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="features-interactive">
    <title>Interactive Platforms</title>
    <para>PLplot device drivers support the following platforms that are suitable for interactive plotting:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>GDI</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>GTK+</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PyQt</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Qt</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Tcl/Tk</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>wxWidgets</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>X</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="acquiring-plplot">
    <title>Obtaining Access to PLplot</title>
    <para>
      PLplot is a SourceForge project and may be obtained by
      the usual SourceForge file release and anonymous git repository access that is made
      available from links at
      <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/plplot">http://sourceforge.net/projects/plplot</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="installing">
    <title>Installing PLplot</title>
    <para>
      The installation procedure is by necessity system specific;
      installation notes for each system are provided in
      <xref linkend="os-notes"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      After PLplot has been configured, built, and installed, you can write code in
      C or any of the languages that have PLplot bindings
      to make the desired PLplot calls.  Example programs in all supported
      languages are included with the PLplot software package.  The
      installation of those examples includes both a CMake-based
      build system and a more traditional (Makefile + pkg-config) build system
      for building and linking the examples to help guide users
      to build and link their own code for compiled languages or dynamically
      load PLplot for scripting languages.
      Plots generated from these example programs are shown
      <ulink url="http://&PLplot-website;/examples.php">here</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="organization">
    <title>Organization of this Manual</title>
    <para>
      The PLplot library has been designed so that it is easy to write
      programs producing graphical output without having to set up large
      numbers of parameters.  However, more precise control of the results
      may be necessary, and these are accommodated by providing lower-level
      routines which change the system defaults.  The manual first describes
      the overall process of producing a graph using the high-level
      routines (see <xref linkend="simple-graph"/>).  For a discussion of
      the underlying concepts of the plotting process and an introduction
      to some of the more complex routines (see <xref linkend="advanced"/>).
      An alphabetical list of the user-accessible PLplot functions with
      detailed descriptions is given in the reference section of the manual
      (see <xref linkend="API"/>).
    </para>
    <para>
      Because the PLplot kernel is written in C, standard C syntax is used
      in the description of each PLplot function. If you have difficulty
      interpreting the call syntax as described in this manual, please refer
      to part III, Language Bindings. This manual includes:
      C (<xref linkend="c"/>),
      C++ (<xref linkend="cplusplus"/>),
      Fortran 95 (<xref linkend="fortran95"/>),
      Java (???),
      Tcl (<xref linkend="tcl"/>),
      Perl (<xref linkend="perl"/>) and
      Python (<xref linkend="python"/>). Since PLplot has a long
      history, bindings to your language of choice are probably available
      though not necessarily in the PLplot distribution. It is a good idea
      to ask around and do a quick search before rolling your own.
    </para>
    <para>
      The meaning of the function (subroutine)
      arguments is typically the same regardless of what language you are
      using to call PLplot (but there are some exceptions to this).  The
      arguments for each function are usually specified in terms of PLBOOL,
      PLINT,and PLFLT&mdash;these are the internal PLplot representations for
      logical, integer, and floating point, and are typically a zero (false) or
      non-zero (true) contained in a long, a long, and a float (or
      a LOGICAL, INTEGER, and a REAL, for Fortran programmers).  See
      <xref linkend="c"/> for more detail.
    </para>
    <para>
      Most of the output devices supported by PLplot are listed in
      <xref linkend="x-drivers"/> and <xref linkend="output-drivers"/>,
      along with description of the device driver--PLplot interface,
      metafile output, family files, and vt100/tek4010 emulators.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="copyrights">
    <title>Copyrights</title>
    <para>
      The PLplot package may be distributed under the following terms:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
      This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
      modify it under the terms of the GNU Library General Public
      License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
      version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

      This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
      but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
      Library General Public License for more details.

      You should have received a copy of the GNU Library General Public
      License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA.
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      The text of this license is given in the file COPYING.LIB in the
      distribution directory.  Exceptions are noted below.
    </para>
    <para>
      The intent behind distributing PLplot under the LGPL is to ensure that
      it continues to evolve in a positive way, while remaining freely
      distributable. Note in particular that either open-source or
      proprietary code can be linked to LGPLed code such as PLplot, see the
      interpretation <ulink
      url="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/license-list.html">here</ulink>.
      Full details of the LGPL are given <ulink
      url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html">here</ulink>.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="additional-copyrights">
      <title>Additional Copyrights</title>
      <para>
	The start up code used in argument handling
	(<filename>utils/plrender.c</filename> and
	<filename>src/plargs.c</filename>) is partially derived from
	<filename>xterm.c</filename> of the X11R5 distribution, and its
	copyright is reproduced here:
      </para>
      <programlisting>
	******************************************************************************
	Copyright 1987, 1988 by Digital Equipment Corporation, Maynard,
	Massachusetts, and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge,
	Massachusetts.

	All Rights Reserved

	Permission to use, copy, modify, and distribute this software and its
	documentation for any purpose and without fee is hereby granted,
	provided that the above copyright notice appear in all copies and that
	both that copyright notice and this permission notice appear in
	supporting documentation, and that the names of Digital or MIT not be
	used in advertising or publicity pertaining to distribution of the
	software without specific, written prior permission.

	DIGITAL DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE, INCLUDING
	ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL
	DIGITAL BE LIABLE FOR ANY SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR
	ANY DAMAGES WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS,
	WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
	ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS
	SOFTWARE.
	******************************************************************************
      </programlisting>
      <para>
	Any file that is explicitly marked as "public domain" is free
	from any restriction on distribution.
      </para>
      <para>
	Any file that has a explicit copyright notice may be distributed
	under the terms of both the LGPL and whatever stated conditions
	accompany the copyright.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="credits">
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>
      PLplot 5.0 was created through the effort of many individuals and
      funding agencies.  We would like to acknowledge the support
      (financial and otherwise) of the following institutions:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The Institute for Fusion Studies, University of Texas at Austin
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The Scientific and Technology Agency of Japan
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Japan Atomic Energy Research Institute
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Duke University
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Universite de Nice
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  National Energy Research Supercomputer Center
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Los Alamos National Labs
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Thanks are also due to the many contributors to PLplot, including:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Tony Richardson: Creator of PLplot 2.6b, 3.0
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Sam Paolucci (postscript driver)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Sam Paolucci (postscript driver)
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Tom Rokicki (IFF driver and Amiga printer driver)
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Finally, thanks to all those who submitted bug reports and other
      suggestions.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
