<!-- -*-  mode: nxml -*- -->
<!--
    intro.xml: "Introduction" chapter

Copyright (C) 1994  Geoffrey Furnish and Maurice LeBrun
Copyright (C) 1999-2017  Alan W. Irwin
Copyright (C) 1999, 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004  Rafael Laboissiere
Copyright (C) 2003  Joao Cardoso

Redistribution and use in source (XML DocBook) and "compiled" forms
(HTML, PDF, PostScript, DVI, TeXinfo and so forth) with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
met:

1. Redistributions of source code (XML DocBook) must retain the
above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following
disclaimer as the first lines of this file unmodified.

2. Redistributions in compiled form (transformed to other DTDs,
converted to HTML, PDF, PostScript, and other formats) must
reproduce the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and
the following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other
materials provided with the distribution.

Important: THIS DOCUMENTATION IS PROVIDED BY THE PLPLOT PROJECT "AS IS"
AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,
THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE PLPLOT PROJECT BE LIABLE
FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR
CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF
SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR
BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY,
WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR
OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS DOCUMENTATION,
EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
-->

<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <sect1 id="plplot-plotting-library">
    <title>The PLplot plotting software</title>

    <para>PLplot is a &features-cross-platform; software package for
    creating scientific plots whose (<ulink
    url="http://www.utf-8.com/">UTF-8</ulink>) plot symbols and text are
    limited in practice only by what <ulink
    url="http://www.utf-8.com/">Unicode</ulink>-aware system fonts are
    installed on a user's computer. The PLplot software, which is
    primarily licensed under <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html">the LGPL</ulink>, has a
    clean architecture that is organized as a core C library, separate
    language &features-bindings; for that library,
    and separate device drivers that are dynamically
    loaded by the core library which control how the plots are presented
    in &features-noninteractive; and &features-interactive; plotting
    contexts.</para>

    <para>The PLplot core library can be used to create standard x-y
    plots, semi-log plots, log-log plots, contour plots, 3D surface plots,
    mesh plots, bar charts and pie charts. Multiple graphs (of the same or
    different sizes) may be placed on a single page, and multiple pages
    are allowed for those device formats that support them.</para>

    <para> PLplot has core library support for plot symbols and text
    specified by the user in the UTF-8 encoding of Unicode. This means for
    our many Unicode-aware devices that plot symbols and text are only
    limited by the collection of glyphs normally available via installed
    system fonts. Furthermore, a large subset of our Unicode-aware devices
    also support complex text layout (CTL) languages such as Arabic,
    Hebrew, and Indic and Indic-derived CTL scripts such as Devanagari,
    Thai, Lao, and Tibetan. Thus, for these PLplot devices essentially any
    language that is supported by Unicode and installed system fonts can
    be used to label plots.</para>

    <para>
      PLplot was originally developed by Sze Tan of the University of
      Auckland in Fortran-77.  Many of the underlying concepts used in the
      PLplot package are based on ideas used in Tim Pearson's PGPLOT
      package.  Sze Tan writes:
      <blockquote>
	<para>
	  I'm rather amazed how far PLPLOT has travelled given its origins
	  etc. I first used PGPLOT on the Starlink VAX computers while I was
	  a graduate student at the Mullard Radio Astronomy Observatory in
	  Cambridge from 1983-1987. At the beginning of 1986, I was to give a
	  seminar within the department at which I wanted to have a computer
	  graphics demonstration on an IBM PC which was connected to a
	  completely non-standard graphics card. Having about a week to do
	  this and not having any drivers for the card, I started from the
	  back end and designed PLPLOT to be such that one only needed to be
	  able to draw a line or a dot on the screen in order to do arbitrary
	  graphics.  The application programmer's interface was made as
	  similar as possible to PGPLOT so that I could easily port my
	  programs from the VAX to the PC.  The kernel of PLPLOT was modelled
	  on PGPLOT but the code is not derived from it.
	</para>
      </blockquote>
    </para>

    <para>The C version of PLplot was originally developed by Tony
    Richardson on a Commodore Amiga.  That version has been improved and
    expanded ever since first by Geoffrey Furnish and Maurice Lebrun in
    the 1990's and later (after the project was registered at SourceForge
    on 2000-02-23) <ulink
    url="&PLplot-website;/credits.php">with a much-expanded
    development team.</ulink></para>

    <para>
      We welcome suggestions on how to improve this code, especially in the
      form of user-contributed enhancements or bug fixes.  If PLplot is used
      in any published papers, please include an acknowledgement or citation
      of our work, which will help us to continue improving PLplot.  Please
      direct all communication to the <ulink
      url="https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/plplot-general">plplot-general
      mailing list.</ulink>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="features">
  <title>Feature Summary</title>
  <sect2 id="features-cross-platform">
    <title>Cross Platform</title>
    <para>PLplot is currently known to work on the following platforms:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Linux, Mac OS X, and other Unices</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>MSVC IDE on the Microsoft version of Windows (Windows 2000 and later)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Cygwin on the Microsoft version of Windows</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>MinGW-w64/MSYS2 on the Microsoft version of Windows</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>For each of the above platforms, PLplot <link
    linkend="plplot_configure_build_install">can be configured, built, and
    installed</link> from <ulink
    url="&PLplot-website;/downloads.php">source</ulink>, and for the Linux
    and Mac OS X platforms third-party binary packages for PLplot <ulink
    url="&PLplot-website;/downloads.php#Binary_Packages">are
    available</ulink>.</para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="features-bindings">
    <title>Language Bindings</title>
    <para>The language bindings of the C PLplot library are currently the following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Ada</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>C++</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>D</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Fortran 95</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Java</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://common-lisp.net/project/cl-plplot/">Lisp</ulink></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Lua</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>OCaml</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Octave</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://search.cpan.org/~dhunt/PDL-Graphics-PLplot">Perl/PDL</ulink></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Python</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Tcl/Tk</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="features-noninteractive">
    <title>Output File Formats</title>
    <para>PLplot device drivers support the following plotting file formats:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>CGM</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>GIF</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>JPEG</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PBM</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PDF</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PNG</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PostScript</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>SVG</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Xfig</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="features-interactive">
    <title>Interactive Platforms</title>
    <para>PLplot device drivers support the following platforms that are suitable for interactive plotting:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>GDI</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>GTK+</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PyQt</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Qt</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Tcl/Tk</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>wxWidgets</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>X</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="acquiring-plplot">
    <title>Obtaining Access to PLplot</title>
    <para>
      PLplot is a SourceForge project and may be obtained by
      the usual SourceForge file release and anonymous git repository access that is made
      available from links at
      <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/plplot">http://sourceforge.net/projects/plplot</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="plplot_configure_build_install">
    <title>Configure, build, and install PLplot from source</title>
    <para>After the source code for PLplot <ulink
    url="&PLplot-website;/downloads.php">has been obtained</ulink> the generic
    steps to configure, build, and install PLplot are as follows:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Optionally set environment variables to force
      CMake's find commands to locate any of PLplot's software dependencies
      that are installed in non-standard locations.  See the CMake
      documentation for the <ulink
      url="https://cmake.org/cmake/help/latest/command/find_file.html"><literal>find_file</literal></ulink>
      and <ulink
      url="https://cmake.org/cmake/help/latest/command/find_library.html"><literal>find_library</literal></ulink>
      commands for the list of such variables which includes
      <literal>CMAKE_INCLUDE_PATH</literal>,
      <literal>CMAKE_LIBRARY_PATH</literal>, and <literal>PATH</literal>.
      In addition, the <literal>PKG_CONFIG_PATH</literal> environment
      variable forces CMake to find certain software packages which specify
      their (non-standard) install locations using <literal>pkg-config</literal>.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Optionally set environment variables that force CMake
      to use specific compilers to override the (normally good) default
      choice of compilers that CMake uses.  The environment variables that
      CMake recognizes for this purpose are <literal>ADA</literal> to
      specify the Ada compiler, <literal>CC</literal> to specify the C
      compiler, <literal>CXX</literal> to specify the C++ compiler,
      <literal>DC</literal> to specify the D compiler, and
      <literal>FC</literal> to specify the Fortran compiler.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Optionally set environment variables that force CMake
      to use specific compiler flags.  The environment variables that CMake recognizes for this
      purpose are <literal>ADAFLAGS</literal> to specify the Ada compiler flags,
      <literal>CCFLAGS</literal> to specify the C compiler flags,
      <literal>CXXFLAGS</literal> to specify the C++ compiler flags,
      <literal>DFLAGS</literal> to specify the D compiler flags, and
      <literal>FFLAGS</literal> to specify the Fortran compiler flags.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Prepare for running the <literal>cmake</literal> command
      by removing the stale PLplot install tree (if it exists) that corresponds to
      the <literal>-DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX</literal> option for the
      <literal>cmake</literal> command (see below), creating an empty build directory, and
      changing directories to that build directory (which will become the top-level directory
      of the build tree).
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Configure the PLplot build and install by running
      <programlisting>
	cmake &lt;cmake options&gt; &lt;top-level directory of the source tree&gt;
      </programlisting>
      on the command line. Many <literal>cmake</literal> options are possible.  Two common ones that are
      often sufficient for most purposes are
      <literal>-DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=&lt;installation prefix&gt;</literal> (to specify the
      top-level directory of the soon-to-be created install tree) and <literal>-G &lt;generator identification string&gt;</literal>
      (to identify the <literal>cmake</literal> backend generator to use such as "Unix Makefiles").  However, there are also
      many other <literal>cmake</literal> options that are
      specific to the PLplot build system that
      are documented in the <filename>CMakeCache.txt</filename> file that
      is created by the <literal>cmake</literal> command.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Build PLplot by building the "all" target.  For example, that would
      be done for the "Unix Makefiles" generator case by
      <programlisting>
	make all
      </programlisting>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Install PLplot by building the "install" target.  For example, that would
      be done for the "Unix Makefiles" generator case by
      <programlisting>
	make install
      </programlisting>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Determine the list of additional targets that are available for the
      PLplot build by building the "help" target.  For example, that would
      be done for the "Unix Makefiles" generator case by
      <programlisting>
	make help
      </programlisting>
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    For additional platform-specific details beyond the above generic
    steps, please consult <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/p/plplot/wiki/Home">our wiki</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para> After PLplot has been configured, built, and installed, you can
    write code in C or any of the languages that have PLplot bindings to
    make the desired PLplot calls.  Standard example programs in all
    supported languages are included with the PLplot software package.
    The installation of those examples includes both a CMake-based build
    system (see <filename>&lt;installation
    prefix&gt;/share/plplot&Project-Version;/examples/CMakelists.txt</filename>)
    and a more traditional (Makefile + pkg-config) build system (see
    <filename>&lt;installation
    prefix&gt;/share/plplot&Project-Version;/examples/Makefile</filename>)
    for building and linking the examples.  Either of these two build
    systems can be adapted by users to build and link their own
    PLplot-related code for compiled languages or to test PLplot related
    code that is compiled or which is written in a scripting language
    where PLplot capability is dynamically loaded.  However, note the
    CMake-based build system for the installed examples should work on all
    platforms where PLplot can be built while the traditional build system
    for the installed examples will only work on platforms (e.g., Linux)
    which have <literal>make</literal> (only with GNU extensions),
    <literal>pkg-config</literal>, and <literal>bash</literal> (required
    for testing targets) installed.  Plots generated from these example
    programs as well as the source code for those examples in all our
    supported languages are available from links given <ulink
    url="&PLplot-website;/examples.php">here</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="copyrights">
    <title>PLplot Copyright Licensing</title>
    <para>
      PLplot is free software that is primarily licensed under the
      LGPL (version 2 or any later version at the option of the user).  The
      exact text of that license is given in the file
      <filename>COPYING.LIB</filename> that is distributed with PLplot.  The
      free software licenses that are used for the parts of PLplot not distributed
      under the LGPL are explicitly noted in the
      <filename>Copyright</filename> file that is distributed with PLplot.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="credits">
    <title>Credits</title>
    <para>Many developers have contributed to PLplot over its long history.  For further details see
    <ulink url="http://plplot.sourceforge.net/credits.php">our credits page</ulink></para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
