<?xml version='1.0' encoding='us-ascii'?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY examples '<ulink
   url="http://plplot.sourceforge.net/examples/index.html">example
   web page</ulink>'>
]>

<sect1>
  <title>Announcement of PLplot-5.3.0</title>

  <sect2>
    <title>Release Notes</title>

    <para>
      The <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/project/memberlist.php?group_id=2915">PLplot
      development team</ulink> is proud to announce the release of version
      <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=2915">5.3.0</ulink>
      of the <ulink url="http://plplot.sf.net">PLplot</ulink> scientific
      plotting library.  This version of PLplot comes out nine months after
      the latest release (5.2.1) and represents a considerable amount of
      development work, as documented in the <ulink
      url="ChangeLog-5.2.1-5.3.0">ChangeLog</ulink> of CVS activity.  The
      main focus of this release is the strengthening of <quote>niche
      occupation</quote> by PLplot.  Indeed, two of the traditional core
      language bindings (C++ and Fortran 77) are highly improved, and the
      configuration/build system became more robust, allowing successful
      installations in platforms like MacOS X and Cygwin.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Changes</title>

    <sect3>
      <title>API</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    With this release, the ABI (Application Binary Interface)
	    backward compatibility of the PLplot library has been broken,
	    because the libraries libnn and libcsa were renamed to
	    libcsironn and libcsirocsa, respectively.  For this reason, the
	    soversion number had to change.  In Linux, for instance, the
	    libraries are called now
            <filename>libplplot*.so.9.0.0</filename>.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <function>plsabort</function>: New function.  Similar to
	    plsexit, should be used to set a handler for the
 	    <function>plabort</function>.
	    function.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <function>plot3d</function>: Plot a contour only if the number
            of points in the contour is greater than zero.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <function>plshade</function>: Fixed corner case when argument
            <literal>pltr == NULL</literal> and contouring is wanted.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <function>plgriddata</function>: Arguments have type PLINT now,
            consistent with the rest of the API.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <function>plline</function>: Fill clipping improved.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Language Bindings</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The C++ API has been totally rewritten, with 13 API additions,
	    most notably the command-line parsing functions. The interface
	    is much more modern now and the demos were revamped. Several
	    backward incompatibilities have been introduced, such that the
	    <filename>libplplotcxx</filename> has a separate soversion
	    number now, independent of that for the C PLplot library.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The API for Fortran 77 was completed and should be more
            portable.  It includes the functions for parsing command line
            options, as well as plstripc-, plshade- plmesh-, and
            plsurf-related API functions.  The examples were rewritten and
            mimic the C examples closely.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Java stubs are collected into a loadable module instead of
            in a library as before.  Setting
            <literal>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</literal> is not required anymore.
            Also, there is no need for using <literal>CLASSPATH</literal>.
            Since the Java interface is now mature, its building is enabled
            by default.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            PLplot support was included in the latest version of <ulink
            url="http://pdl.perl.org">PDL</ulink> (the Perl Data Language).
            Porting of the C PLplot demos to Perl has started and the first
            file is included in this release
            (<filename>examples/perl/x01.pl</filename>).  The PDL bindings
            are likely to evolve a lot in the near future, and the C demos
            will be ported progressively.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Many Octave demos are improved now, in particular those
            featuring mouse interactivity.  Although the bindings are still
            compatible with the 2.0 series of Octave, compatibility at the
            script level is only guaranteed for the 2.1 series.  However,
            there are some issues with the latest version of Octave
            (2.1.53) and, for this reason, Octave bindings build is
            disabled by default in configure.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Drivers</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The drivers for Windows (DOS/djgpp, Win32/msdev, and win-tk)
            have been updated and should work in this release.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The line width setting in the ps/psc driver is fixed and the
            results are visually equivalent to those obtained with the
            other drivers.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In the xwin driver, a window resizing bug is fixed.  This bug
	    appeared when several windows were used in a pthreaded
	    application.  Also, the xwin driver uses now by default pthreads
	    as well as <quote>default visual</quote>.  To disable them, the
	    user has to use <quote><literal>-drvopt
	    usepth=0</literal></quote> and <quote><literal>-drvopt
	    defvis=0</literal></quote>.  Note that the
	    <literal>usepth</literal> option is only effective when PLplot
	    is configured <literal>--with-pthreads</literal> (which is now
	    disabled by default).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Config/Build/Install</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Autotools-based PLplot configuration became much more
            robust.  The autoconf/automake/libtool constructs have been
            modernized and several combinations of configuration options
            work better in this release.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Use of <quote><literal>make prefix=/some/path
            install</literal></quote> for setting the installation prefix
            works now.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Compliance with the <ulink
            url="http://www.pathname.com/fhs/">FHS</ulink> (Filesystem
            Hierarchy Standard) is being pursued.  The architecture
            independent data files are now installed in
            <filename>${prefix}/share/plplot&lt;version&gt;</filename>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The previous support for a local defaults file for configure
            has been removed in favor of the built-in CONFIG_SITE support.
            The reconfig script is made permanent and not automatically
            generated as before.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Checks for C compiler NaN awareness are improved (this is
            necessary for compiling the libcsironn/csa libraries).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Python and Swig configuration code is more robust now.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <ulink
            url="http://www.freedesktop.org/software/pkgconfig/">pkg-config</ulink>
            support has undergone a total rewrite and should be much more
            portable with this release.  It is activated with option
            <literal>--with-pkg-config</literal> to configure.  The
            plplot-config script is still kept as an alternative to the
            pkg-config support.  See the installed
            <filename>example/&#42;/Makefile</filename> for examples of
            use.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When developing the PLplot library itself, developers do not
            need to install the whole package in order to test/evaluate the
            changes.  This is implemented through the new core function
            <function>plInBuildTree</function>, and the new configuration
            variable <literal>BUILD_DIR</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Library core</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Memory management fixes: almost all of the memory leaks
            revealed by <ulink
            url="http://valgrind.kde.org">valgrind</ulink> are gone.  There
            are still some problems under investigation and fixes to them
            will be integrated in the next release.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The third-party libraries libcsironn and libcsirocsa were
 	    updated to versions 1.38 and 0.22, respectively.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Almost all compilation warnings messages disappeared, even when
            compiling with <literal>gcc -Wall</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <function>plOpenFile</function>: sane use of stderr and stdout.
            This function respects the option <literal>-debug</literal> now.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Re-enabled the setting of the <literal>tcl_cmd</literal>
            internal option (only affects <literal>plrender -dev
            tk</literal>).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Documentation</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The PLplot Documentation in DocBook format is released now
            under Free Software terms, with a license similar to
            the <ulink
            url="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/ln16.html">FreeBSD
            Documentation License</ulink>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The HTML form of the documentation uses <ulink
            url="http://www.w3c.org/Style/CSS/">CSS</ulink> (Cascade Style
            Sheets) now.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Tests</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The test suite <filename>test/plplot-test.sh</filename> fully
            works for all front-ends.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>

    <para>
      The following PLplot core developers actively participated in this
      release: Joao Cardoso, Vincent Darley, Alan W. Irwin, Rafael
      Laboissiere, Maurice LeBrun, Arjen Markus, Andrew Roach, and Andrew
      Ross.
    </para>

    <para>
      Several people participated as testers and/or helped to port PLplot
      to different systems and architectures: Koen van der Drift, Ullal
      Devappa Kini, Rob Managan, Per Persson, Michel Peyrard, Valerij
      Pipin, Olof Svensson, and Brian D. Wright.  Many others have
      participated to discussions in the plplot-devel and plplot-general
      mailings lists.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title></title>
    <para role="signature">
      Rafael Laboissiere, 2004-02-02
    </para>

    <para role="foot">
      <ulink url="../index.html">PLplot home page</ulink> | <ulink
      url="announce-plplot-5.3.0.txt">Text version</ulink> |
      <ulink url="announce-plplot-5.3.0.xml">XML source</ulink> |
      <ulink url="Makefile">Makefile</ulink>
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
